Finding Aid for Netherlands America University League Records, 1976-1999.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Netherlands America University League records 1976-1999
Netherlands America University League.
2 linear feet
89178 Bimu N301 2
Organization established to promote contact among people at the University of Michigan and in the Ann Arbor, Michigan, area who came from the Netherlands, also those who have worked or studied there, and those who share an interest in the social, cultural, and scientific life of the Netherlands. Consists of administrative records and topical files documenting the activities of the organization.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from the Netherlands America University League in 1987 (Donor No. 7443 ).
The record group is open to research.
Organized in 1976 by the late Jan de Vries, a medical doctor on the faculty of the University of Michigan School of Public Health, the Netherlands America University League (NAUL) took its name from an earlier group that had been active during World War II. Present NAUL members Ali and Don Riddering had been part of the original group from 1953 to its demise in 1958. They joined Jan and Janet de Vries, Bert and Riet Haas, and Paul and Mary Jane van den Muysenberg in organizing the reincarnated NAUL. Its purpose would be "to promote contact among people at the University of Michigan and in the Ann Arbor area who came from the Netherlands, have studied or worked there, or have other contacts with that country." Later this aim was broadened to include those who share an interest in the social, cultural, and scientific life of the Netherlands. Following the initial meeting on December 3, 1976, NAUL experienced increased membership and expanded its presentations of public programs on various aspects of Dutch culture and society. It also became active in supporting existing programs in the university including the Visiting Netherlands Professorship and the Visiting Lecturer in Dutch Language and Literature. In 1981, under Jan de Vries' energetic leadership, a Dutch Writer-in-Residence program was initiated through the cooperation of the Department of German Language and Literature and the Center for West European Studies, with financial support from the Dutch Ministry of Culture.
In order to provide a sounder basis for financial support of its activities, NAUL was incorporated as a nonprofit, tax-exempt organization in 1980. The first board members were Jan de Vries, president, Ali Riddering, vice-president, Riet Haas, secretary, Bert Haas, treasurer, Paul van den Muysenberg, Charles Butter, Loren Barritt, and Percival Price.
NAUL programs and events reached a peak in activity during 1981/82 on the occasion of the bicentennial celebration of the Netherlands-America treaty of Comity and Commerce, the first treaty between the fledgling United States and a foreign power. The year was highlighted by the visit of the painter Karel Appel and included a series of films by Philo Bregstein, 1981/82 Writer-in-Residence, exhibits of Dutch art works at the U-M Museum, performances of Dutch music at the School of Music, and lectures on Dutch social problems, literature, and history. The celebration culminated in the visit of Queen Beatrix and Prince Claus to the university in June 1982.
The Netherlands America University League records consists of administrative records and topical files documenting the activities of the organization. The files have been divided into two series: Administrative Records and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Dutch--Michigan.; Netherlands.; University of Michigan.
- Administration
  The Administrative Records series includes articles of incorporation, bylaws, and history; committee records; correspondence; minutes; and NAUL newsletters.
  - Articles of Incorporation / By-Laws (Box 1)
  - Board members 1998/1999-1999/2000 (Box 1)
  - Budget, Treasurer's Reports
    - 1976-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1993 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Fundraising Committee (Box 1)
    - Hospitality Committee 1983-1987 (Box 1)
    - Membership
      - 1980-1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1990 (Box 1)
    - Nominating Committee 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Program Committee 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    - Publicity (Box 1)
    - Scholarship Committee-DeVries-Van der Kooy Memorial Scholarship (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Corporate Fund Raising Solicitation 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Dutch Area Studies 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Inter-university Project
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - 1982 (Box 1)
    - Netherlands Government
      - The Hague
        - 1918-1984 (Box 1)
        - 1984-1987 (Box 1)
      - Washington Embassy 1978-1984 (Box 1)
      - Chicago Consulate-General
        - 1977-1984 (Box 1)
        - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
      - Detroit Consul 1976-1987 (Box 1)
      - Holland (Mich.) Consul for Press and Cultural Affairs (Box 1)
    - Snoek, Kees, Lecturer in Dutch Languages and Literature 1977-1983 (Box 1)
    - Stichting ter Bevordering van de Vertaling (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1978-1999, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - History and informational brochures (Box 1)
  - Interest Survey (Box 1)
  - Library
    - List of Dutch literary works in English translation in NAUL Library (Box 1)
    - Holdings of Dutch materials in University of Michigan libraries (Box 1)
  - Mailing lists and membership material
    - 1981-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1990 (Box 1)
  - Membership lists (Box 1)
  - Minutes and Annual Reports
    - 1980-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991-1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, include guest book (Box 2)
  - Newsletters
    - 1977-1984 (Box 2)
    - 1985-1992 (Box 2)
    - 1993-1999 (Box 2)
  - Office 1980-1986 (Box 2)
  - Officers responsibilities (Box 2)
  - Survey of Members 1991 (Box 2)
- Topical files
  The Topical Files series documents the activities and programs of the organization, notably the Writer-in-Residence Program. The Guest Lecturers' files contain correspondence with, and other information about, the various speakers. Some press material about performances may also be found in the Program Announcements file. The arrangement within each folder is generally chronological.
  - Activities and Projects
    - Amsterdam Poets' Circus (Box 2)
    - Dada Dutch 1990 (Box 2)
    - Ethnic Fair, Ann Arbor 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - Netherlands-America Bicentennial Celebrations (general) 1980-1982 (Box 2)
    - Netherlands-America Bicentennial Cultural Festival 1982 (Box 2)
    - Rotterdam Philharmonic Reception 1977 (Box 2)
    - Ten Year Anniversary 1986 (Box 2)
    - World's Fair, (Washtenaw Community College) 1977 (Box 2)
  - Program Files
    - Announcements and Posters
      - 1977-1984 (Box 2)
      - 1985-1999 (Box 2)
    - Guest Lecturers and Speakers
      - 1981/82 (Box 2)
      - 1982/82 (Box 2)
      - 1983/84 (Box 2)
    - Program Planning
      - General (Box 2)
      - Jorvis Ivens Film Exhibit (Box 2)
    - Writer-in-Residence Program
      - General (Box 2)
      - Bert Schierbeck 1981/82 (Box 2)
      - Philo Bregstein 1982/83 (Box 2)
      - Misch de Vreeds 1983/84 (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1970-1985 (Box 2)